KIRAN KUMARI (UP CM FELLOW)

Email ID-Kiranofficial95@gmail.com Phone No-8638028568/8876242080

Working as CM FELLOW under UP CM Fellowship Programme at Planning Department, Govt. of Uttar Pradesh where roles and responsibilities includes inspection and monitoring of govt. schemes. Also worked Entrepreneurship Expert with Humana People to people India in project called UDYOGINI in Jhajhar District of Haryana, roles in current job is that developed enterprise on large scale. Also Young Professional with a demonstrated work experience at ongoing Ministry of Rural Development Program i.e., HSRLM public sector livelihood program. Worked with Haryana State Rural Livelihoods Mission for the upliftment of the skills amongst the women and providing timely input and monitoring for the cluster level federation. Skilled in Communication, Teamwork, and Community Engagement. Strong social development professional with a Master of Social Works degree focused in Livelihood and Social Entrepreneurship from Tata Institute of Social Science. Interested in interdisciplinary department convergence, supportive supervision, monitoring and evaluation.

WORK EXPERIENCE

14 November 2022–Present

WORKING AS CHIEF MINISTER FELLOW UNDER UP CHIEF MINISTER FELLOWSHIP PROGRAMME

- The roles and responsibility include the concurrent evaluation work of all the schemes run by the Central / State Government in the aspirational development block.
- Inspecting the implementation work of all government scheme and monitoring the operation of the schemes and to provide the desired benefits to the public from the schemes.

15 March 2022-30 October 2022

WORKED AT HUMANA PEOPLE TO PEOPLE INDIA

- → Stakeholders interaction for linking with relevant government scheme, skill service providers financial institutions for finalizing and startup/ scaling up nano and micro entrepreneurial project for long term sustainability

June 2019-14th March 2022

WORKED WITH HARYANA STATE RURAL LIVELIHOOD MISSION (HSRLM), FATEHABAD DISTRICT

- **♣** Interdepartmental Convergence.
- ♣ Being an Additional Block In-charge learned the system of NRLM Mission and other dynamics
- ♣ Formation & Strengthening community based institutions
- ♣ Promoting digital transactions and Community cadre
- **4** Facilitating in imparting training.
- Promoting Sustainable livelihood
- ♣ Work closely with the project facilitation team &community cadres by visiting

- the grass roots institution i.e. SHG, VOs, producers groups, CLFs
- **♣** To prepare guidelines, implementing quality pilot & projects
- Supporting Block & District team and rolling out the project
- ♣ Drafting proposal, booklet, and many other reports for District Administration
- ♣ Management of staff of AKMC

RESEARCH WORK / ACADEMIC LEARNING:

March - BLOCK FIELD WORKS AT OPM India Pvt. Ltd.:-OXFORD POLICY April 2019 MANAGEMENT PATNA BIHAR

- Research on Secondary Source and transcription in terms of ICDS, ANM and ASHA.
- ♣ Assisted in other activities like making power point, Matrix and Questionnaire.

October – November

BLOCK FIELD WORK AT (NEDFi) NORTH EASTERN DEVELOPMENT FINANCE CORPORATION LTD

2018

- ♣ Created new project on Banana Fiber "The potential of banana fibre in handloom and handicraft sector in Ghograpar (Bagurumba weavers development trust, Assam)".
- Organized awareness workshop for livelihood opportunities with regard to the above project.

May 2018 INTERN AT MAHILA SHAKTI KENDRA, BALIPARA ASSAM

♣ Engaged in social Resource Mapping with villager, communities and School at district Tejpur in Garogaan.

March - BLOCK FIELD WORK AT PRATHAM EDUCATION FOUNDATION, BIHAR STATE April 2018 UNIT

- ♣ Worked with Supplementary and Digital Education among school children and drop out female students and others activities such as KGBV, TOLA SEWAK.
- ♣ Capacity building of women from JEEVIKA Self Help Group regarding education of children

October – November

BLOCK FIELD WORK AT MKSS (MAZDOOR KISHAN SAKTI SANGATHAN) RAJASTHAN DEVDUNGRI

2017

- → Survey with regards to Public Distribution system. Community mobilization and awareness regarding the PDS.
- ♣ Worked at advocacy level regarding the use of technology for database of the villagers. Conducted village meetings as a tool for accounting policy implementation.

June 2017 WORK WITH PROJECT CONCERN INTERNATIONAL (PCI)

♣ Worked with Jeevika and participated in SHG to promote significance of well-being of pregnant women and to analyses the development of SHG in the district of Nalanda, Bihar.

April- INTERN AT VAC (VILLAGE ADMINISTRATIVE CENTRE) SOUTH SIKKIM May2016 MELLIPAYON.

- Worked in South Sikkim as an intern in Village Administrative Centre of Mellipaiyong Gram Panchayat Unit.
- Data collection and data entry as instructed By the VAC for the then Proposed E governance initiative for India's first Cyber village Project.
- Successfully presented a survey report on the village on various sectors like education, health, agriculture and livelihood.

May 2015 INTERN AT PAJHRA, ASSAM

Experiential learning at Promotion and Advancement of Justice, Harmony and Rights of Adivasis (PAJHRA) Dhekiajuli, District: Sonitpur, Assam) on the topic: Family Marriage and Kinship at PAJHRA.

PROJECT/DISSERTATION

DISSERTATION THESIS OF M. A. IN SOCIAL WORK IN LIVELIHOOD AND **April 2019 SOCIAL ENTREPRENEURSHIP:**

♣ The Green Economy worker: A study on contributions of manual scavengers(Study in Patna District of Bihar)

DISSERTATION THESIS OF B. A. IN SOCIAL SCIENCES: **April 2017**

4 The female street vendors in Guwahati city: A study of health issues and problems.

EDUCATION

July 2017-	Masters of Arts in Social work specialization in Livelihoods and Social
May 2019	Entrepreneurship from Tata Institute of Social Sciences
•	
July 2014-	BA in Social Sciences from Tata Institute of Social Sciences
April 2017	

ACHIEVEMENT

 28^{th} 2nd March 2021

February- Presented paper on a study on convergence Action at the Grassroots during covid-19 pandemic at the 8th ISWC and 8th ICSDAP conference 2021 jointly organized by National Association of Professional social workers in India, International consortium for social Development-Asia pacific and Department of social work. Visva Bharti, Santiniketan, West Bengal

LANGUAGE & SKILLS

Language:-Hindi, English

Skills:Research Administration, Reports and Proposal writing, Documentation Designing, Training and Development, Leadership & management, participatory Rural Appraisal(PRA) tools, Community mobilization, Group work, case work and Efficient Computer skill

REFERENCE

Manoj Kumar (HCS) (CEO-DRDA--Fatehabad,Haryana) drdaftb@gmail.com Mr. Ranvijay (Former DPM--Fatehabad, Haryana) Ranvijay.hsrlm@gmail.com **Dr. Razdan Sarim Rahman** (Assistant Professor--TISS) Razdan.rahman@tiss.edu